(影山飛雄･ﾅﾚｰｼｮﾝ)
＜中学に上がたら
When I entered junior high, an incredible player was there.
すげぇ選手がいた＞
＜中学て
すげぇとこなんだなて思た＞
It made me think that junior high must be an amazing place.
＜でも
そういうわけじゃなかた＞
Best Setter Award
Oikawa Tooru
But that wasn't the case.
Best Setter Award
Oikawa Tooru
＜その人がすごかたんだ＞
It was him that was amazing.
≪この人を超えれば
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
If I can outperform him,
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
まずは県で１番のセタだ≫
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
I'll be the best setter in the prefecture!
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
Certain
Victory
Kitagawa First Junior High
(他校生)すげぇ烏野のセｯタ
Karasuno's setter is amazing.
１年なのに及川に張り合てる
It's hard for a first-year to hold his own against Oikawa!
ザ･セタ対決て感じだな
It's like "Clash of the Setters."
(日向翔陽)すげぇじゃん
大王様に負けてねぇぞ影山
That's awesome! You're every bit as good as the Great King, Kageyama!
たとえ総合力
県ナンバ１の人だろうと
I don't care if I'm up against the
best overall player in the prefecture.
セタとしては負けねぇ
As a setter, I'm just as good.
でもお前次サブだよな
後衛だよな
But you have to serve next, don't you?
You're in the back row, right?
次も同じのやるて
後衛でツアタクは
Can you do the same thing as before?
Isn't a dump from the back row illegal?
反則なんじゃ
うせぇつ次
Shut up!
I-I meant I'd do it the next time I'm up front!
前衛に回てきたらてことだよ
ぷぷ
Aoba Jousai                    Karasuno
(澤村)影山ナイサ
Episode Twenty:
Oikawa Tooru is No Prodigy
Kageyama, give us a good serve!
≪やべ
(花巻)アウトアウト
Crap!
It's out!
(岩泉)
盛大にフカしたな
He really sent it flying.
(及川)なんて
すごいホムランだ
What a great home run.
≪くそ
(澤村)ドンマイドンマイ
Shit.
Shake it off!
I'm sorry!
すいません
(及川)
それじゃあお手本を見せようか
All right, maybe I should show you how it's done.
Olé!
(菅原)≪え西谷狙い
He aimed it at Nishinoya?!
(西谷)≪正面いや曲がる≫
Straight on!
No, it'll curve!
おお及川のサブ上げた
He took a serve from Oikawa!
(他校生)烏野のリベロすげぇ
Karasuno's libero is incredible!
(２人)ああ
(ハルカ)取ちゃた
Aw, they got it.
Oh dear. That guy is good.
あ痛ぁやぱすごいな
何がお手本だ
Isn't that how it's done?!
普通に拾われてんじゃねぇか
えへへ
He retrieved it like any other ball!
Send it to me!
来いや
(岩泉)１０番１０番
It's number ten!
しゃ
よし
Yes!
Good!
Did you see what happened on the right?
(嶋田)見たな今ライトの方
(滝ノ上)おう
Yeah.
駒の
セタがやてたなそういや
Wasn't it Nekoma's setter who could distract with a glance?
あんな神業トス
反則だよまたく
His superhuman sets should be illegal, darn it.
I'm amazed Nishinoya got that up.
(武田)
よく上げましたねぇ西谷君
あでも
西谷君に打ちゃたのは
But do you suppose Oikawa only accidentally sent the ball to Nishinoya?
及川君の失敗だたのかな
(繋心)
いや西谷を狙たんだと思う
No, I think he aimed it at Nishinoya.
(武田)え
(繋心)西谷が取れないてだけで
If Nishinoya failed to receive the ball,
it'd really demoralize the rest of the team.
Well done!
Thank you!
ほかのメンツに与える
精神的ダメジは大きい
Do another one just like that!
Yes, sir!
それを
狙たんじゃねぇかな
I think that's what he was after.
≪助かた≫
Thank goodness.
You did good getting that one, Nishinoya.
≪本当に
よく上げてくれた西谷≫
I'm sorry. I keep getting suckered.
(金田一)すみません
俺引掛かてばかで
あの伊達工をも翻弄した
烏野だからね
We're against a team who had Date Tech at their mercy.
まあちょとだけ待てよ
Anyway, give it a minute.
たぶんもうすぐだから
It should be any time now.
The real matter is, Kindaichi.
それより金田一よ
(金田一)ん
You must be plenty upset that your place as
Kageyama's partner got taken over by that small fry.
影山の相棒の座を
あのチビちゃんに奪われて
さぞ悔しいことだろう
いや別に
No, not really—
いいんだいいんだ
中学時代飛雄がお前を
It's okay, really.
So what if Tobio thought of you as a useless servant in junior high?
あんま使えない下僕だと
思ていたとしてもな
この及川さんが
神業速攻なんか使わなくても
So what if Yours Truly can't do their trifling superhuman fast attack?
金田一はちゃんとすごいんだぞと
証明してあげよう
We'll prove to him that you're amazing in your own right.
(及川)安心して跳べ
ははい
You're good to jump.
Y-Yes, sir!
ピ
(菅原)田中ナイサ
Tanaka, give us a good one!
(山口)ナイサ
(岩泉)渡
A good one!
Watari!
(渡)はい
(花巻)ナイスレシブ
Got it!
Nice receive!
Center!
センタ
≪Ａクイク≫
A Quick!
(青城応援団)わあ
Rule the Court
いいぞいいぞ勇太郎
押せ押せ勇太郎もう一本
(澤村)
なんだろうな気のせいかな
Is it just my imagination?
あの１２番練習試合のときより
I think their number twelve is jumping higher than he did in the practice match.
高く跳んでる気がする
ピ
Aoba Jousai                    Karasuno
Iwa, give us a nice serve!
(澤村)すまんカバ
はい
Sorry, cover it!
Okay!
トスくれ
Give me a set!
ピ
(観客たち)わあ
Hmm?
で)先生先生
Teach! Hey, Teach!
Aoba Jousai                    Karasuno
What? Seijou is already calling a timeout?
え青城もうタイムアウト
早くない
Isn't it too early?
烏野に流れが行きそうて感じでも
なかたのに
It didn't seem like Karasuno was about to steal the momentum.
(及川)
たぶん間違てないと思います
I don't think I'm mistaken.
｢来い｣と｢くれ｣です
It's "send" or "give."
(菅原)
もしかしてもう気付かれた
Have they already figured it out?
早ぇなくそ
Damn, they're fast.
(及川)最初はさチビちゃんが
何か叫びながら突込んでいくな
At first, I was like, "Wow, the small fry likes to shout as he dives in."
Give it to me!
It made me think maybe he forgot to pay his brain bill.
頭悪そうだな
くらいに思てたんだけど
神業速攻のときは
｢持てこい｣とか｢俺に来い｣とか
Until I noticed that when they do their superhuman fast attack, he says "send it my way" or "send it over here."
｢来い｣て単語が入てるぽい
で普通の速攻のときは
Phrases with the words "send it."
And when they do normal fast attacks...
(岩泉)｢くれ｣て単語か
(及川)うん
They use the words "give me."
でもね
あのチビちゃんの武器は囮
However, being a decoy is the small fry's weapon.
彼にばかり目が行けば
それこそ向こうの思うツボ
They want us to divert all of our attention to him.
だから簡単な決まり事だけ
作ちゃおう
That's why we're going to adopt simple operating procedures.
｢来い｣のときはチビちゃんの
マクは１人だけにしよう
When we hear the words "send it," we'll mark only him.
｢くれ｣のときはトスが
どこに上がるか見てから跳ぼう
When he says "give me," we'll wait to see the set, and then jump.
オケイ
(一同)おす
Okay?
Yessir!
だけどよこんな序盤の
Still, won't they realize that we've figured it out by taking a timeout so early in the match, when nothing is going on?
特に動きのないタイミングで
タイム取て
気付いたことに
気付かれたんじゃねぇの
Let them!
いいのいいのむしろ
気付いてくれた方がいい
That would actually be advantageous.
こちがあの合図に
気付いたことが分かれば
If they realize that we're on to them...
きと多少なりとも飛雄は焦る
I'm almost certain it'll make Tobio lose his cool.
(西谷)おい深刻な顔して
らしくねぇなぁ
Hey, why so serious? That's not like you!
(田中)いやノヤさんこいつは
大体いつもこんな顔だ
I beg to differ, Noya.
This is how he normally looks.
牛乳か飲むヨグルトで
迷てるときも同じ顔だぞ
He makes this face when he dithers between milk and drinking yogurt.
You... I... That isn't true!
そち
そんなことないですよ
(田中)しかしノヤさん
あのサブよく一発で返したな
But, Noya, I really am amazed you managed to receive that serve!
(西谷)俺中坊んとき
あのサブ取たことあるわ
I've received that serve before back in junior high.
確かに
入ればすごいサブだたけど
It really was an amazing serve when it made it through,
結構ミスもしてたし
あんなコントロルもなかた
but it also missed a lot,
and never had that degree of control.
相当練習したんだろうな
He must've really worked on that.
１人サブが
すごいヤツがいるとか
I think it would take more than having one guy with impressive serves
セタが万能とか
それだけでずと
４強でいられるとは思えねぇ
or one really good setter to stay in the top 4.
気ぃ抜いたら持てかれる
気張るぜ
Keep sharp or they'll take it away.
Let's pull it together!
Yeah!
パギャ
Bleagh!
｢パギャ｣てなんだ｢パギャ｣て
ミスても下向かない
Right on!
What is "bleagh" supposed to mean?!
Never look down even if you mess up!
ハフィ
さあ仕掛けていこうか
Now let's set the trap.
金田一
狙うとこ分かてるよね
Kindaichi, you know where to aim, right?
はい
一本
Yes, sir!
One point!
Behind any powerful setup...
(及川)
≪どんなすごいセｯトアｯプもね
is a good, initial receive.
最初のレシブがあるから
できるんだよ≫
ピ
(岩泉)金田一ナイサ
Kindaichi, give us a good one!
(東峰)あ
(武田)あらら
Weird. That serve didn't seem that powerful.
I'm sorry, I'll get the next one!
そんなに強いサブには
見えませんでしたけど
Shake it off!
(東峰)あ
(青城一同)よしゃ
Yes!
(東峰)≪取りづらいな≫
It's hard to receive it.
≪これは後衛のセタの
出てくる所を狙てんのか≫
Are they aiming for where the setter moves from back row to front?
及川君みたいなサブ
打てないのに
He's not serving like Oikawa,
so why can't the opponent receive it?
相手が取れないのなんで
(滝ノ上)おほん
Ahem!
ああそれはですね
(ユウコハルカ嶋田)え
Ah, yes. About that.
Back
Front
When the setter is in the back row,
(滝ノ上)セｯタは後衛にいるとき
サブが打たれる瞬間まで
Back
he may not get closer to the front than the players in the front row until the serve is made.
Front
Back
前衛の選手よりも
前に出てちゃいけないのね
Front
Back
だから
相手がサブを打つと同時に
That's why he must move quickly to the net the moment the opponent serves the ball.
Back
ネト際まで素早く
移動しないといけないんだ
Back
そういう人が交錯する場所は
The receive is momentarily delayed where the
players crisscross, so it's easy to make mistakes.
レシブに入るのが一瞬
遅れたりしてミスしやすい
でも来る場所さえ
分かたら
But as long as they know where the serve is coming...
Kindaichi, give us a good serve!
(東峰)しゃ
(滝ノ上)取れないサブじゃない
Yes!
...it's not impossible to receive.
Nice receive!
ナイスレシブ
ピ
いろいろ考えながらやてんだぁ
Yes!
They really use their heads in this sport.
(ハルカユウコ)おじさん
ありがとうございます
Thank you, Mister!
Mister?!
(滝ノ上)おじあはい
(嶋田)へ
Sure.
(武田)
あここで及川君前衛ですか
Now Oikawa is in the front row.
Number three!
またツアタクにも
気をつけないと
We'll have to be on guard for the dump again.
Give us a good one!
≪くそ
すげぇプレシャだ≫
Damn, this pressure is crazy.
≪もう４点差だし≫
There's already a four point gap.
≪こちは
日向なしで前衛は２枚≫
We have two in the front row minus Hinata.
≪早くロテ回さねぇと≫
We need to move our rotation!
(田中)ナイスレシブ
Nice receive!
≪ツアタク
Setter dump!
(及川)焦てるときのツほど
止めやすいものはないよね
Nothing's easier to prevent than a rushed setter dump.
Aoba Jousai                    Karasuno
ソアハイヤ
Hiyah!
ピ
(２人)しゃ
Yes!
Boo-ya!
Four more points, and we'll turn it around!
(田中)あと４点
軽くひくり返すぜ
Boo-boo-ya!
ソイソイ
(及川)元気だなぁ
You're so perky.
そんで厄介だねぇ
ピ
That's what makes you so annoying.
トスくれ
(２人)あ
Give me a set!
(及川･((｢くれ｣のときは
トスを見てから
When he says "give me," wait to see the set.
(金田一)≪跳ぶ≫
He's jumping!
ふんぬ
く
All right!
≪やぱり気付いてるか
They must've figured it out.
ピ
(田中)影山ナイサ
Kageyama, give us a good one!
One point!
(西谷)一本
ふぅ
This time, I won't miss!
≪今度は外さねぇぞ≫
ちと前すぎか
It's too far forward!
(花巻)あ
よしうまく軟打に切り替えた
Go forward!
Good, he adjusted for a soft hit!
そう簡単には
チャンスにしてやんないよ
I won't let you get your chance that easily!
(武田)影山君がファストタｯチ
トスを上げられない
Kageyama got the first touch!
He won't be able to set!
(澤村)田中
ふんくそ
Tanaka!
Shit.
≪とさに
ピンチをチャンスに変える≫
He turned a tight situation into an opportunity.
≪それが
本番でできるという強さ
That's true strength under pressure.
He didn't learn the sport like the rest.
試合の慣れ方が違う≫
(菅原)ドンマイドンマイ
(山口)もう一本
Shake it off!
One more point!
(武田)
あここでまた及川君のサブ
Now the serve is back to Oikawa.
(及川)いつも威勢のいい
ムドメカが
Nothing feels more oppressive than when the usual big-talking, mood-maker goes silent.
おとなしくなたときの
空気の重さたら
Olé!
Nothing!
(及川)ないよね
(青城応援団)それ
Haikyuu !!
う
ピ
Yes!
(青城一同)よしゃ
(澤村)ドンマイ次一本
Sh-Shake it off! Go for the next point!
Flubbing consecutive serve receives can build up incredible pressure.
≪サブレシブの連続ミスは
相当なプレシャになる
まずは
元気な坊主君を静かにさせて
You start by silencing the perky cueball.
Next, the ace.
次はエス攻撃の要の
レフト２人が折れれば
Breaking the two left wing spikers so pivotal to their offense
優秀な囮も意味をなさない≫
will render the excellent decoy meaningless.
(及川)ん
That was fast!
早
即行でタイム取たな烏野
All right!
Karasuno sure didn't wait to take a timeout.
That's because Seijou has the momentum.
ただでさえ
流れは青城だからな
They need to stop their momentum
before it becomes impossible to reverse.
早く流れ切らないと
取り返しつかなくなる
I feel sorry for the guy they're targeting.
(他校生)
狙われてるヤツかわいそう
(繋心)上でいい
セタに返らなくても
Just keep it up!
Even if you can't get it back to the setter, someone can always cover it as long as you keep it in the air.
上に上げさえすれば
どうとでもカバできる
Yessir!
(田中)うす
(繋心)ところで影山君よ
By the way, Mister Kageyama.
What was that last dump of yours supposed to be?
さきのツは
あれはなんだね
I'm sorry, sir!
すんませんした焦りました
(繋心)ふぅ
I lost composure.
As long as you're aware of it, that's fine.
自覚があんならいいや
ツがダメなんじゃない
Dumps aren't the problem.
攻撃のバリエションが
多いてことを
It's beneficial to let our opponents be aware that we have a good variety of attacks.
相手に
認識させておくのも有効だ
But dumps are nearly always stoppable once they're on to you.
ただツは読まれたらほぼ
止められるからリスクが高い
使いどころは慎重に選べよ
うす
Choose when to use them carefully.
Yessir.
Next, don't forget who we're playing against.
あと
何と戦てんのか忘れんなよ
We're playing against Aoba Jousai, not Oikawa.
及川じゃなく青葉城西だ
Also, you're not playing them alone. We play as a team!
それで戦てんのは
お前だけじゃなく烏野だ
うす
Yessir.
(岩泉)ナイサ
(花巻)もう一本
Give us a good one!
One more point!
Olé!
うあ
上がた
It's up!
ピ
Rule the Court
オケオケ
ちゃんと上がてるぞ田中
Looking good!
You're getting them up in the air, Tanaka!
Yessir!
うす
ピ
(西谷)龍
日向カバ
Ryuu!
Hinata, cover it!
Yessir!
はい田中さん
(岩泉)５番５番
Tanaka!
It's number five!
ピ
ち
Sir!
先生
はい
Right!
タイムアウト
２回とも使ちまたか
Now we've used up both our timeouts.
Stopping their momentum is the top priority.
ここは流れを切ることが
最優先だからな
繋ぎが命のバレで
With volleyball, it's all about keeping the ball in play,
so nothing feels worse than the guilt and loneliness that comes from repeatedly flubbing the vital serve receive.
肝心要のサブレシブを
連続でミスてるときの
あの罪悪感と孤独感は
尋常じゃない
Then they add insult to injury by shutting him out.
(滝ノ上)しかも
そこに追い打ちのドシャト
あの坊主大丈夫か
Is the guy with the crew cut gonna be okay?
≪何か言た方がいいのかな
Should I say something to him?
≪俺へこみそうになると
Tanaka always encourages me when I start to cave in.
田中さん
いつも何か言てくれるし
俺も何か
I should say something.
Um...
あの
ふんぬ
(田中)すんませんした
(西谷)龍
I apologize!
Some things can't be avoided, Ryuu!
しょうがないこともあんだろ
今のトスは難しかたし
That last set was real difficult, and you had a triple block on you. I failed to back—
３枚ブロクだたし
俺もフォロ
I failed to call for the set!
俺今トス呼ばなかた
I freaked out for a second. Dammit!
一瞬ビビたんだちくしょう
後悔は試合が終わてから
クソほどする
I'll do a shitload of regretting once the match is done!
大して取り柄もねぇ俺が
I have no real redeeming qualities,
so there's no use dragging down the team by caving over my own mistakes!
てめぇのミスに勝手にへこんで
足引張てちゃ
どうしようもねぇ
次は決めます
I'll make it count the next time!
今それを言えることが
十分取り柄だ
The ability to say that is one heck of a redeeming quality!
Yessir.
(田中)あうす
It'll bounce off you by using your arms alone, so move your feet.
(繋心)腕だけで取ろうとすると
はじかれるから足動かせよ
旭さんも
龍みたいになるといいですよ
Asahi, you should try to be more like Ryuu!
I would if I could!
できたらやてるよ
You know, I noticed this during that last timeout,
なあ
さきのタイムのときもだけどさ
but isn't Oikawa acting a little weird?
及川てヤツ様子おかしくない
(他校生)ああ
Yeah. He says he does that so he won't break his concentration.
それ集中力切らさないように
してんだてさ
Most teams take timeouts to stop the momentum of those dangerous serves.
あのヤバいサブの流れ
切るためにほとんどのチムは
タイム取るから
(一同)さ来い
Now, bring it!
Oikawa, get another point!
≫及川もう一本
Give us a nice serve!
Damn, he has full concentration.
(繋心)≪くそ
しかり集中してやがる
あとはお前らで
どうにかするしかねぇぞ≫
The rest is up to you guys.
Olé!
If it bounces off me at a weird angle, it's all over! I have to receive it!
(田中)
はじいたら終わり受け止めろ
(他校生)下手したら顔面だぞ
That could've hit him in face!
Shit, it's falling!
≪くそ落ち
くは
うらぁ
(武田)おお返した
(繋心)それもいちばんいい所に
They sent it back!
And in the best possible spot.
渡ち
はい花巻さん
Watacchi!
Yes, sir! Hanamaki!
ナイスレシブ
Nice receive!
Sorry! Cover it!
すまんカバ
レフト
Left!
田中さん
Tanaka!
It's not as though he doesn't make mistakes.
(繋心)≪ふだんから
ミスが少ないわけじゃない≫
And he's sensitive to jeers.
≪すぐ
挑発に乗ちまたりする≫
But not only is he the most powerful player second to Asahi,
≪でも
東峰に次ぐ
チムナンバ２のパワと
何より
崖ぷちに追い込まれたときに
he has the mental fortitude to maintain his performance when he's at the brink.
パフォマンスを落とさない
メンタルの強さ≫
(繋心)≪紛れもない
It's indisputable.
(繋心)≪エスの資質≫
He has the makings of an ace.
ピ
おお烏野の坊主自分で
Ooh! The short-haired guy from Karasuno did it for himself!
及川に持てかれた流れ
He took the momentum that Oikawa stole from them...
Yes!
しゃあ
(他校生)切た
...and stopped it!
Tanaka!
Ryuu!
Aw, I was still good for a few more points.
あと３４点は
取るつもりだたのになぁ
Tanaka!
Nice!
Guys, thanks for the awesome backup!
Whoa, that was my clearest look at a block ever!
うおお今までで
いちばんブロク見えた
ん
たまにな
There are times I can see the opponents' block real clear in midair, like in slow motion.
空中でスロモションみたく
相手のブロクが
見えることがあんだよ
Almost like light is shining through it.
こうスと光が通たみたいに
おお
Tanaka, that's so cool!
田中さんかけぇ
わははは先輩だからな
Because I'm your upperclassman!
Tanaka, serve!
(澤村)田中サブ
(田中)はい
Yes, sir.
≪流れは切た≫
The momentum has been stopped.
Aoba Jousai                    Karasuno
≪まだ序盤ここから追い上げる≫
It's still early in the match.
We can still catch up.
(東峰)ナイスワンタチ
チャンスボル
Nice job getting a hand on it!
We have a chance here!
Send it my way!
来いや
ピ
よしゃ
All right!
He's too fast even when we know he's coming!
≪来るの分かてても速ぇな≫
Hey, you!
おいこらまだトスはかなわない
なんて言うんじゃねぇだろうな
You'd better not tell me you still can't beat his sets.
You mean Tobio's? Of course I can't beat him.
飛雄にかなわないよ
I can't do pinpoint sets like he can.
あんなピンポイント
上げられないし
ぎゃ怒んないで
Don't get mad!
Tanaka, give us a good serve!
Sure, I can't beat his talent, but I know I can produce the sets you all hit the best.
才能ではかなわなくても
みんながいちばん打ちやすい
トスを上げる自信はあるよ
ピ
だからセタとしては負けない
So I'm as good of a setter as he is.
ピ
It got in above the block again.
≪またブロクの上から
Don't look so surprised.
≪そんなに
びくりすることはないよ≫
This has always been Kindaichi's optimum striking point.
≪これが金田一の本来の
最高打点なんだからさ≫
ピ
(澤村)前前
Forward!
Aoba Jousai                    Karasuno
≪７点差なんとか詰めないと≫
A seven point gap.
Nice receive!
We need to stop their momentum!
Send it my way!
ピ
おお
He's looking sharper than ever!
なんだかいつもより
キレがある感じだなぁ
≪くそブロク２枚
結構ついてくるな≫
Shit.
I'm sorry, I was a little too late.
A double block. They're keeping up with us.
That was close!
≪ここで止められたら
また流れが持ていかれる≫
Shake it off! You'll get the next one.
If they stop us now, they'll have the momentum again.
Yes, sir. I'll do my best!
I need to lose one blocker.
≪せめて１枚にしないと≫
(及川)＜高校２年のとき
When I was in my second year of high school,
I heard the nickname of a brilliant player in junior high.
優秀だた
中学の後輩の異名を聞いた＞
＜コト上の王様＞
"The King of the Court."
I thought, wow, what a prestigious nickname.
＜なんて
誉れ高い異名だと思た＞
But once I watched him play,
I knew it meant something else.
＜でも試合を見て
意味が違うと分かた＞
＜力がある才能がある＞
He has the power. He has the talent.
He wants to win more than anyone else I know.
＜勝利に対しても貪欲
他人よりも圧倒的に＞
Those elements make Tobio tough,
＜それが飛雄を強くしそして
but they're also a weakness.
唯一の弱点になる＞
≪お前は一人でなんとかしようと
しすぎなんだよ飛雄≫
You always try to do everything by yourself, Tobio.
≪そして
ほんのふた月足らずじゃ
And it's only been about two months.
It takes longer than that to cure a bad habit.
その癖は簡単には直らないよ≫
(岩泉)花巻ナイスキ
(金田一)ナイス
Hanamaki, nice spike!
Nice!
Boo-ya!
(２人)ソイ
(菅原)日向
Hinata!
例の合図な作戦変更だ
うほ
You know the signals we talked about? It's time to change our strategy.
Do you mean we're using the new ones?
もしかして新しいやつ
(澤村)カバ
Cover it!
Matsukawa, nice block!
(岩泉)松川ナイスブロク
く
I've got it!
オライ
(澤村)もかいもかい
One more time!
Hey, is it just me, or is Karasuno's offense gradually speeding up?
なあなんか烏野の攻撃
だんだん速くなてきてないか
I don't like this acceleration.
≪嫌な感じの加速だ≫
≪タイムは
もう使いきちまたし
We've already used up our timeouts.
Go slow! Don't lose your cool!
ゆくりゆくり焦んなよ
It's a collective speed trance.
(入畑)スピドの呪縛
ブロクから逃れたい一心で
They want to dodge the blockers so badly, they accidentally prioritize speed over ease and accuracy.
つい打ちやすさよりも
速さを優先してしまう
無意識にほんの少しずつ
でもそれは
Subconsciously and ever so gradually
it steadily leads to bigger miscalculations.
徐々に大きなズレになていく
≪飛雄お前は天才だ
Tobio, you're a prodigy.
あのチビちゃんであんな攻撃を
使えるのはお前しかいない
You're the only one who can pull off those attacks with the small fry.
でもほかはどうだ
But how about the rest?
Don't you think if you set it more slowly to your number three,
３番の彼はもう少し
ゆたり上げてあげれば
he would have the caliber to compete with our blockers?
ちゃんとブロクと勝負できる
力量があるんじゃないのか
メガネ君はお前のトスを信頼して
本気で打ているか
Does Four-eyes truly trust your sets when he hits that ball?
≪個性の違うスパイカたち
All spikers are unique.
Only a true setter can bring out all their strengths...
それぞれ１００％の力を
引き出してこその
completely.
(及川)≪セタだ≫
ピ
(青城応援団)わあ
Aoba Jousai                    Karasuno
It's no good.
≪ダメだ差が縮まらねぇ≫
The gap isn't shrinking.
≪なんとかなんとかしないと≫
(澤村)≪ネトを越える
I need to do something, anything!
It's over the net!
Push it back, Kageyama!
(澤村)押し込め影山
ピ
(青城応援団)わあ
It's like Kageyama isn't himself somehow.
(山口)なんか
いつもの影山じゃないみたいだ
(田中)ナイスレシブ
Nice receive!
I'll be damned if I'll lose!
≪負けてたまるか
負けてたまるか
I refuse to lose!
≪勝てコトに残るんだ
I have to win and stay on the court!
(２人)あ
(西谷)旭さんナイスフォロ
(岩泉)チャンスボル
Asahi, nice backup!
We have a chance here!
Oikawa is talented, and he puts in a good effort.
≪及川はセンスもある
努力も惜しまない≫
≪ただ２つ年下の
But when you compare him to a whiz like Kageyama, two years his junior...
影山という
才能の塊と比べたとき
Oikawa is a class act, but he is no prodigy.
及川は優等ではあるが
天才ではない≫
Yet, I can still say with certainty,
the better setter of the two right now...
≪それでも断言できる≫
≪今の段階で
セタとして優れているのは
及川であると≫
is Oikawa.
ピ
Aoba Jousai                    Karasuno
Next Episode Preview
A swap now?
(滝ノ上)このタイミングで交代か
(嶋田)ああ
Yeah, that's so painful.
あれつらいんだよな
コトから出るとき
It's hard to hold your head up high when you leave the court.
顔上げらんなくてさ
(滝ノ上)でもさ嶋田
But dude, Shimada.
お前ずと控えだたよな
(嶋田)あ
You've always been a bench warmer.
Oh.
Episode Twenty-one:
The Talented Upperclassman
Next time on Haikyuu!!:
"The Talented Upperclassman."
おとといからの大雨で､兵庫県丹波
市では
流れ込んだ土砂で住宅が倒壊し
この家に住む男性が遺体で見つか
た
警察などによると､午前７時前､